<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-04-29T18:34:53+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AI APIs in Healthcare</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-APIs-in-Healthcare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI APIs in Healthcare" /><published>2023-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-APIs-in-Healthcare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/AI-APIs-in-Healthcare/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>People are thinking that the new best people in any field will be the people 
who know how to use AI the ‘best way.’ They know how AI can best combine with their creative
mind and efforts. They may be right or absolutely wrong.</p>

<p>AI developers are working to democratize AI, to bring a no-code workspace but still modify the 
AI to more of their liking. To take their expert knowledge and augment the AI with it. Then maybe 
when we get this, physicians and doctors won’t be frustrated that neural networks are ‘black boxes.’ 
Instead they can be like a puppet steering the AI in the right direction and checking if the math 
behind the scenes is leading to the right results.</p>

<p>So as of today, what are the AI APIs in healthcare that do this sort of thing?</p>

<h2 id="technology-apis">Technology APIs</h2>
<p>In the healthcare world, technology API companies are growing and becoming unicorn companies. Optum,
under the same creators of UnitedHealth, is one of the biggest data analytics arms for healthcare 
companies to directly plug in. Healthcare is very complicated, so if a tool doesn’t provide any 
overhead stress but makes life easier, it’s a good pitch.</p>

<p>There are also APIs like Particle Health. As an introduction, healthcare requires great security, 
anonymization, so if we wanted to have an API where hospitals could access patient records just from
their name we wouldn’t be able to. It’d be extremely helpful to hospitals, but also lead to needing
cybersecurity teams constantly battling the hacking going on (while billions of records are at risk). 
What Particle Health does is instead use patient demographics to find a patient and all of their 
records; it’s a great and simple idea!</p>

<p>Brendan Keeler in his new quirky post on April 10 called “Super Integration Fighter III” splits software into the “atomic units,” databases, user interfaces, and system interfaces.</p>

<p>Healthcare tends to outsource a lot of things to APIs (especially now with physician burnout on a high where it’s better for tech to do some of the jobs). Keeler talks about how when we get to the optimal stage, of any hospital or clinic being able to access a patient’s data or use an API that connects all patients, we’ll have to throw away the idea of tech siloes. It’ll be hard but either there’ll need to be a common data format (like FHIR which makes it easy) or even what would be interesting, a way hospitals could easily change the API for their use case with low-code.</p>

<p>I really want to talk about this part, about getting the power of APIs in the hospital’s hands and obviously with AI, because that’s been my craze for a long time and now on everybody else’s trending page.</p>

<h2 id="ai-no-code-software">AI No-Code Software</h2>
<p>After searching around, there is not much research on AI low-code or no-code software IN HEALTHCARE. We’ve heard 
of AI being used for finding similar gene expressions, for making DNA/RNA sequencing cheap, but what about deployment? 
AI will accelerate, but now hasn’t really, but let’s look at how AI low-code software will work practically?</p>

<p>Brainstorming a few applications off my mind</p>
<ul>
  <li>If a doctor doesn’t agree with the AI model say taking an image and predicting cancer, the doctor can type into the AI their
reasons and the AI might augment its prediction (we’re not there yet).</li>
  <li>More API-style, you tell your AI your use case and they look through the EHR to find what information you need (this could be really cool)</li>
  <li>AI APIs don’t just need to be doctor facing but can also be patient-facing helping them distill hard-to-understand medical information</li>
</ul>

<p>With all the processing tasks, my imagination of low-code is there are differences across each clinic? Can you find some way to embed information in the AI that tells them because of this difference, do this task this way. Because there are common use cases, but a billion different data formats, a billion different little things to do. If we get every sort of data to be machine-readable, throw away the idea of a common data format (like FHIR), we’ll let the AI do its work!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I think what this is getting at is what we call multi-task learning in AI. An AI tried out a bunch of different data problems. Now the AI knows I can use how I solved all these other problems, to solve this new problem, even though it looks 
different! And this is how academics learn, how people learn. Researches have tried different neural networks, RNN, ANNs, Transformers, hundreds of times, and they have some intuition on what model they should use for a new problem.</p>

<p>Instead of the billions of different AI applications we’re seeing (like AI art-generation, AI text-generation, AI Q&amp;A) I think we achieve real human-computer interaction when you can talk to it in some sort of semi machine-human language (not code) and it can do whatever you want.</p>

<p>Then again, I wouldn’t think it would be frustrating if it was like a vending machine or a drink machine, where you click what application you want (text generation, art generation, Q&amp;A). That’ll only be $1.50 (vending machine joke). Then the machine figures how to do the task for your set of data. It’s all interesting, futuristic, and awesome!</p>

<p><i>Goodnight even though it’s not night,
yall!</i></p>]]></content><author><name>Akshat Mundra</name></author><category term="healthcare" /><category term="machine-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how AI is being brought to medical experts with no AI expertise]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unsupervised learning is weird!</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/unsupervised-learning-is-weird/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unsupervised learning is weird!" /><published>2023-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/unsupervised-learning-is-weird</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/unsupervised-learning-is-weird/"><![CDATA[<p>Unsupervised learning is a very weird world. Imagine you are walking
down a park, sit on a bench, and then get some wise words from an older person.
The words don’t make any sense, but somehow they give structure to your life. I am
not sure many of you have had that experience, but unsupervised learning uses nothing
(except some scientist’s statistical techniques) to find structure in the data.</p>

<p>Monty Python (oops I mean Monty Hall) is also a weird problem but statistics tell us the answer.
In this post, I’m going to pull infamous examples of unsupervised learning that have blown scientists
away!</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
   <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
       <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/montyhall.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

   </div>
</div>

<h1>tSNE embeddings with Brawl Stars</h1>

<p>One interesting unsupervised technique is <a href="https://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume9/vandermaaten08a/vandermaaten08a.pdf">tSNE embeddings</a>. The S stands for stochastic, which means an ‘estimation.’ The classic example is a ball rolling down a hill, but you have no idea where the ball is going to end up. Now comes an example related to what we love, playing Brawl Stars! As a brawler, you’re noticing hmmm let’s draw a boundary here. After all, we can’t have Crow
and Leon attacking each other right in the start! Now let’s continue drawing boundaries, until we have a pretty fair map!</p>

<p>For the non Brawl-Star readers, first of all, I’m sorry. Hopefully you’ve heard of the game Catan. Everyone knows
the process of changing the hexagons so no stones are nearby, no 3 adjacent hexagons are too powerful. That is a
‘stochastic’ description of how tSNE works, but instead of setting the Catan board up or creating a Brawl Stars map,
it’s taking high-dimensional data and transforming it into low-dimensional data. The idea is that data points nearby
in high dimensions should also be nearby in the transformed dimensions (e.g. Leon and Leon should be close together,
but not Leon and Crow).</p>

<p>A really nice explanation with visualizations is <a href="https://www.enjoyalgorithms.com/blog/tsne-algorithm-in-ml">here</a>.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
   <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
       <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/brawl.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

   </div>
</div>

<h5>What has tSNE been used for?</h5>
<p>Imagine <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-13056-x">RNA expression levels for thousands of genes from up to millions of cells”</a>. How do you compare single cells with millions of information? Think about why tSNE is there, because ‘life’ is very complicated (get it haha). And maybe if you find a single cell that on a 2D graph
is near another one that scientists know, you can tell that cell’s purpose. Maybe inside the cell, a gene is being
regulated that is causing a disease.</p>

<p>Or maybe <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/vatsalmavani/music-recommendation-system-using-spotify-dataset">Spotify</a> wants to take the audio features of the song, and based on the songs you like, tell you what other songs you’ll like (e.g. sound similar). Or even maybe Spotify wants to give you vastly different song recs so you can explore your music
taste!</p>

<h2>Zero shot learning</h2>
<p>I don’t know if zero shot learning is an example of unsupervised learning, but the idea is that it
can learn new concepts without have any data. So for example when you were a baby, you saw penguins, koalas,
snakes, pandas, but you never saw a Giraffe. You didn’t even know it was called a Giraffe! So you decided to
call it tall white animal with golden spots.</p>

<p>You don’t need any labels (kind of the idea of unsupervised learning). This paper in 2015 that I have absolutely
not read, but <a href="https://proceedings.mlr.press/v37/romera-paredes15.html">caught my attention</a> because it
discusses how a one-line solution beat SOTA in zero-shot learning. It’s definitely interesting, but that’s all I want
to talk about it for now!</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
   <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
       <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/v7labs.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

   </div>
</div>

<h2>Let's talk about Autoencoders!</h2>
<p>Have I ever heard anyone that excited about autoencoders?! Actually, yes. <a href="http://ufldl.stanford.edu/tutorial/unsupervised/Autoencoders/">A nice read on autoencoders</a>.</p>

<p>Even autoencoders would probably be excited about themselves because they love to learn! Let me explain. The sort of
motivation goes like we love discovering things ourselves without anyone’s help. Let’s give you a neural network and
all you have to do is take your image and output that same image.</p>

<p>But we’re going make life very hard for you! We’re going to add an activation (so you can’t just have weights with 1,
1, 1, 1), we’re going to turn off some of your neurons. It’s hell, but by trying to get out of that hell, the autoencoder learns hey, maybe, if I figure this is grass most of the pixels around are grass. And so on.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
   <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
       <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/hell.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

   </div>
</div>

<p>Unsupervised learning is a very weird statistical world! Put in an input of the Multiverse, you might get an output
of the Rick and Morty-verse. It’s a magical thing!</p>

<p><i>Goodnight even though it’s not night,
yall!</i></p>]]></content><author><name>Akshat Mundra</name></author><category term="math" /><category term="machine-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[just talking about machine learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Substack and healthcare</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/substack-and-healthcare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Substack and healthcare" /><published>2023-02-02T01:51:41+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T01:51:41+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/substack-and-healthcare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/substack-and-healthcare/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[WE NEED LABOR UNIONS ON SUBSTACK... PLS DON'T BAN THIS POST]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Competing incentives in healthcare</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/competing-incentives-in-healthcare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Competing incentives in healthcare" /><published>2023-01-26T14:59:37+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T14:59:37+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/competing-incentives-in-healthcare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/competing-incentives-in-healthcare/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[...doctors are not just evil aliens who want run every possible test to get the most money (they are just optimized to do so)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Update on being gone….</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/update-on-being-gone/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update on being gone…." /><published>2023-01-24T06:12:31+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-24T06:12:31+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/update-on-being-gone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/update-on-being-gone/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Could America’s Healthcare System Become the Netherlands</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/could-americas-healthcare-system-become-the-netherlands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Could America’s Healthcare System Become the Netherlands" /><published>2023-01-22T19:34:45+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-22T19:34:45+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/could-americas-healthcare-system-become-the-netherlands</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/could-americas-healthcare-system-become-the-netherlands/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone on Reddit says it's impossible, because of America's open market policies. However, Netherlands has healthcare + majorly private markets following similar capitalistic policies]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The American Healthcare System Seems Great</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-american-healthcare-system-seems-great/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The American Healthcare System Seems Great" /><published>2023-01-20T03:59:33+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-20T03:59:33+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-american-healthcare-system-seems-great</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-american-healthcare-system-seems-great/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[...on paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The holy grail of healthcare companies: Kaiser Permanente</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-holy-grail-of-healthcare-companies-kaiser-permanente/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The holy grail of healthcare companies: Kaiser Permanente" /><published>2023-01-14T19:23:48+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-14T19:23:48+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-holy-grail-of-healthcare-companies-kaiser-permanente</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/the-holy-grail-of-healthcare-companies-kaiser-permanente/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can we build another Kaiser Permanente? Is it possible?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Everyone is Saying About the Recession’s Effect on Healthcare</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/what-everyone-is-saying-about-the-recessions-effect-on-healthcare/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Everyone is Saying About the Recession’s Effect on Healthcare" /><published>2023-01-07T22:16:31+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-07T22:16:31+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/what-everyone-is-saying-about-the-recessions-effect-on-healthcare</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2023/what-everyone-is-saying-about-the-recessions-effect-on-healthcare/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The second black swan event]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing a Face-Time Doctor Appointment</title><link href="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2022/designing-a-face-time-doctor-appointment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing a Face-Time Doctor Appointment" /><published>2022-12-30T02:30:49+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-30T02:30:49+00:00</updated><id>https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2022/designing-a-face-time-doctor-appointment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoakshat.github.io/blog/2022/designing-a-face-time-doctor-appointment/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For designer nerds in healthcare, and anyone interested in building a telehealth company]]></summary></entry></feed>